גוט טוב, Gut tov, welcome to the last week of מסכת נדה
Masechet Niddah and of the first cycle of the of the learning
of שס. Shas. So this is the very last week of that
and we pick up today's דף Daf is סז, Samech Zayin, but
we are a little bit behind, so we pick up on the
very last three words of סו עמוד א. Samech Vav Amud Aleph.
And we had just seen yesterday amongst a lot of other interesting
things, the critical statement of רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira that the which
has changed almost all of מסכת נדה Masechet Niddah for contemporary practice,
that now we sort of combine, create a hybrid of נדה Niddah
and זבה. Zavah.
Even even the tiniest drop of blood regardless of what time of
the year it is, of the month it is, makes a woman
a זבה, Zavah, a זבה גדולה. Zavah Gedolah. So you sort of
create a hybrid of נדה, Niddah, which it begins with the one
drop of blood, not like זבה Zavah three days, and then you
give it the status of a זבה, Zavah, which is seven clean
days. And we saw that while that there's a whole exchange between
רב פפא Rav Pappa and רבא, Rava, and I want to get
we're going to see more of this in a minute. So this
is why I'm also reiterating it. That רב פפא Rav Pappa sort
of sort of pushed back on the statement of רבא, Rava, he
says how could you say this normal הלכה? Halakha? What about רבי
זירא's Rabbi Zeira statement? And רבא Rava seemed to initially resist, he
says no no no, that's just a מנהג, Minhag, it's not real
הלכה. Halakha. But then a sentence later, רבא Rava gave his ruling
about דם חימוד, Dam Chimud, about when a woman gets propositioned for
marriage and we're concerned that that leads to some spotting of blood
even if you don't see it maybe. And רבא Rava there also
said seven clean days. So although רבא's Rava initially resisting רב פפא's
Rav Pappa sort of trying to universalize the statement of רבי זירא,
Rabbi Zeira, it seems a minute later that he's buying into it.
And we're going to see more of that in a minute. I
should also mention in terms of the issue of דם חימוד, Dam
Chimud, that we basically that's really not relevant today because we sort
of translate it to be just in a case where it's like
a complete surprise that somebody said let's get married. How often does
that happen? Although you have interesting stories in the in the responsa
literature, you know, it also reminds you of some certain Jewish jokes
where anyway, where like of you know, that a village sent over
two guys to marry two other women in the other village, and
one of the guys died and you know you have to decide
is it the new whatever it is. Anyway, these things like is
this a new idea, or like no, it broke off for one
woman so they tried giving her another guy, well since she was
planning on getting married that day anyway, is that really a new
thing because it's just a new guy? Whatever, there's all these very
interesting stories about that. But the real place where that has relevance,
by the way, I would say two things about that before we
move on, is number one, this practice that you go to the
מקוה Mikvah only within four days of the not more than four
days before the wedding night. Some of that connects to somehow interestingly
derived from this based on practices about four days?
I thought it was just a day of no
no, it can't be more than four days before before the wedding
night. Anyway, somehow that interestingly derives from this issue about about how
soon after you're getting ready for the wedding night is the wedding
night occurring. The other interesting thing I should say though is this
practice about not חתן Chattan and כלה Kallah not seeing each other
for a week before the wedding, which actually runs right in the
face of this. This sort of sees that the excitement and surprise
might become lead a woman to become a נדה. Niddah. So if
anything, you don't want to sort of have them, you know, have
this up, you know, big excitement and sexual sort of tension or
whatever, you know, that on that night because, you know, maybe it'll
lead to becoming a נדה. Niddah. If anything, you should try to
be sort of more sort of keep things, you know, settled on
natural like on a non-sort-of-buildup plane, excitement, you know, sort of surprise
plane. And it's interesting that actually in a Jewish Observer many years
ago, so it's in the Jewish Observer so you know it's true,
there was an article that basically shown that basically showed that this
whole idea of not seeing each other the week before is a
completely non-Jewish practice. Really? And yes, completely adopted from some from I
think either a Christian practice or certainly a secular practice, a non-Jewish
practice, and it really runs in the face of
of this הלכה Halakha of דם חימוד, Dam Chimud, which it say
you're not supposed to create like this, you know, shock sort of
like this big thing, you know, right before the wedding. Now some
people say it's still a good idea because there's so much tension
and fighting or whatever right before the wedding, maybe it's better that
you keep your distance. But certainly a couple that wants to see
that see one another and sometimes sort of for pictures or other
things. It's a מנהג, Minhag,
it's a מנהג. Minhag.
My niece, they at my niece at the wedding they greeted the
guests together and this חרדי Charedi family
was...
I know, I know, but I'm telling you.
I understand,
which is why just so nobody should think that it's a crazy
liberal idea that's coming up in this שיעור, Shiur, it was in
the very פרום Frum Jewish Observer, well-documented that this is a non-Jewish
practice, actually you could say that it's אסור Assur for two reasons:
number one, the concern of דם חימוד, Dam Chimud, and number two,
of חוקות הגוים. Chukot HaGoyim. So anyway, so it's interesting what types
of things get adopted and get treated as very פרום. Frum.
So they obviously never learned this מסכת. Masechet.
Alright, now moving on. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, said רבא. Rava. אשה.
Isha. All right, so now turning the page, אשה לא תחוף. Isha
lo tachof. אשה. Isha.
A woman, now that we're moving on from these discussions of דם
חימוד dam chimud and seven clean days, which we will return to
very soon, a woman לא תחוף lo tachof should not sort of
lather her hair, should not wash her hair, לא בנתר ולא בחול,
lo beneser velo bechol, not with נתר, neser, which is some type
of a soap, and חול chol is some type of a sand,
whatever, which is interestingly used as a cleansing agent. בנתר משום דמקטף,
Beneser mishum demikatef, נתר neser because it basically causes hair to fall
out and then it'll get entangled in other hair. ובחול משום דמסריך
Ubechol mishum demasrich
because it causes the hair to stick to one another. So basically,
what we are indicating here is something that the גמרא Gemara in
בבא קמא Bava Kama mentions, which is that עזרא Ezra was מתקן—we
metaken never say this here but it's the background—that עזרא Ezra was
מתקן metaken
that women before they go to the מקוה mikvah do חפיפה. chafifa.
And חפיפה, chafifa, there's a discussion in the ראשונים rishonim what that
includes, but the basic point as we see here is that basically
it means washing the hair, maybe washing and combing the hair, because
the hair is the place where it's obviously hardest to spot if
there are certain types of חציצות. chatzitzos. It also explains why the
emphasis on women, because women tend to have long hair and that
they have to particularly wash and comb their hair before going to
the מקוה mikvah so that there should not be any חציצות, chatzitzos,
any obstructions, any knots naturally in the hair. Is it...?
No, no, no, because of dirt, because
of external stuff, not because... no, no, no. We'll talk about knots
in a minute. Anyway, so that's why... well if it's a knot
in itself I'll talk about that later. Anyway, so that's the practice
of חפיפה, chafifa, which is required to remove any possible dirt or
obstructions or tangles or whatever. And here we're saying it has to
be done with these types of—not with cleansers that are going to
create a bigger problem. I should
well... I'll also mention we'll see in a minute that it's not
so clear that this requirement of חפיפה chafifa did not include bathing
the body before the מקוה. mikvah. It really seems the emphasis was
on the hair, but we'll continue to talk about that in a
minute.
So the concern with these is that the חול chol will get
in her hair and stay there?
Yeah, meaning the first concern to do a washing of the hair
was to get out any natural types of dirt or waste hairs
that would have entangled or other types of חציצות chatzitzos that could
be in the hair. But now he's saying don't try to—don't create
more problems than you're solving and don't use certain cleansers that are
also themselves going to cause a certain amount of hair to get
tangled or...
So what was the נתר neser then?
I don't know, some type of very harsh cleanser that could cause
hair to get pulled out. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אמר אמימר משמיה דרבא, Amar Amemar mishmei deRava, Amemar said in
the name of Rava, אשה לא תחוף אלא בחמין. Isha lo tachof
ela bechamim. She should also when she washes her hair only use
hot water, אבל לא בצונן, aval lo betzonen, but not in cold
water. ואפילו בחמי חמה, Ve'afilu bechamei chama, but when you have to
use hot water, it can even be heated by the sun. It
doesn't have to be super hot, but it shouldn't be
cold. צונן מאי טעמא לא Tzonen mai ta'ama lo? Why can you
not use cold water? משום דקרירי, Mishum dekariri, it's cold, ומשרי זיא,
umeshari zaya, and it causes the hair to—you know I thought ומשרי
umeshari means fall out like נשר, nosher, but anyway רש"י Rashi says
it means that it causes the hair to be hard and therefore,
you know, it does not do a good job getting the dirt
out of the hair. As we know, hot showers are much better
for getting dirt off than cold showers. So again, here are things
in terms of the practice of חפיפה: chafifa: make sure you do
it with the right temperature water and with the right types of
cleansers that it actually gets dirt out and gets חציצות chatzitzos out
and doesn't create problems. Okay, so that's the issue of חפיפה. chafifa.
We will revisit that in a minute. ואמר רבא, Ve'amar Rava, Rava
also says—this is going to be like I told you, the next
few דפים, dapim, dense list, you know, סוגיות, sugyos,
not even very involved סוגיות, sugyos, but almost like very short, dense
listing of a lot of different laws of practical הלכות. halachos.
Like you said, during the nine days you shouldn't take a shower
in...?
Yeah, if you have to do it, not for הנאה hana'ah but
for cleanliness, you definitely can. ואמר רבא: Ve'amar Rava: לעולם ילמד אדם
בתוך ביתו שתהא אשה מדיחה בית קמטיה במים. Le'olam yilamed adam betoch
beiso shetehei isha madicha beis kemateha bemayim.
A person should always teach in his house, meaning a man, *beiso*
meaning his wife. So a man should always teach his wife that,
or שתהא אשה, shetehei isha, that a woman should, or teach it
in his house so maybe to his daughters also, שתהא אשה מדיחה
בית קמטיה במים, shetehei isha madicha beis kemateha bemayim,
a woman should rinse her folds, the folds on her body with
water, which means—you know, like the sort of normal types of like,
you know, way in which like—I don't know, if you're
like—okay, that was good—if
you—like for me, if you have a little—if you could lose a
little bit of weight, there's a little bit of folds like in
the stomach area or there's folds, you know, underneath the arms. There
are places where are not always exposed smooth skin and maybe dirt
collects there. So it says, right, it says make a point, right,
like between your toes, make a point to rinse those off with
water to get out any dirt, any possible obstruction.
At all times, not just...?
No,
before going to the מקוה. mikvah. Oh, he's not just teaching general
laws of cleanliness, he's saying before going to the מקוה. mikvah. Okay,
רש"י Rashi particularly emphasizes underarms and the pubic area, is what רש"י
Rashi emphasizes. Now, מיתיבי, Meisivei, I'll ask you on this: בית הקמטים
ובית הסתרים, Beis hak'matzim uveis has'tarim, the folds and the hidden places—hidden
places are places like cavities in the body that are still sort
of like exposed to the outside air like inside the ear, inside
the... the mouth, inside the vagina. Those are בית הסתרים Beis Hasteraim
where water can get to. They're sort of open to the outside
world, but they're still inner. בית הקמטים Beis Hakematim is the folds
area. Okay, so those types of places אין צריכים לביאת מים, ein
tzrichim l'vias mayim, you don't actually have to get water in there.
You don't have to open your mouth and get water in your
mouth when you go to the מקוה. mikvah. So and you don't
have to actually, you know, stretch out all parts of your body
so that it gets into like into all, you know, underneath all
the folds. Water doesn't have to actually get onto that, it only
has to get onto the exposed part of your skin that's naturally
exposed, not inner, not underneath the fold. So if that's true, why
do you have to clean your ears? You know, it's like that
old joke. The mother says to the kid, like, you know, did
you clean your ears before going to the, you know, whatever, going
to the doctor? He said yes, and he's very upset. Why? Because
you didn't even bother checking there. So, you know, anyway, I don't
know if that was such a joke. Anyway, the point is why
bother doing it if you don't have to actually get it onto
the, get it into, you know, get the water of the מקוה
mikvah to hit? That's the question. So the גמרא Gemara says back:
נהי דביאת מים לא בעינן, nehi d'vias mayim lo ba'inan, it's true
you don't actually need water to get in there, but מקום הראוי
לביאת מים בעינן, makom harauy l'vias mayim ba'inan, it has to be
able for water to get in there. There still are laws of
חציצה. chatzitzah. Although the water doesn't have to hit that place, a
חציצה chatzitzah would still invalidate the טבילה. tevilah. Kind of like רבי
זירא. Rabbi Zeira. דאמר רבי זירא, D'amar Rabbi Zeira, I will explain,
רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira says: כל הראוי לבילה אין בילה מעכבת בו.
kol harauy l'vilah ein bilah me'akeves bo.
There's a law that you have to mix a מנחה, mincha, the
flour with oil. And the גמרא Gemara says that if you can
bring a מנחה mincha up to sixty עשרונים, esronim, you
know, sixty sort of units, עשרונים, esronim, but more than that not
because it's not fit to mix with oil. So the גמרא Gemara
says: Who cares if it's so big you can't mix it with
oil? If we're, if we would say that even if you didn't
mix it with oil, it's still good. He says, okay, it's true
you don't have to mix it with oil בדיעבד, b'diavad, but it
has to be able to be mixed with oil. And that's the
principle of כל הראוי לבילה. kol harauy l'vilah. As long as there's,
as long as it's fit to be mixed with water, then it
doesn't have to actually, which means there are some things, and I'll
discuss this all in a minute, but let's just finish the point.
There are some things that you don't actually have to do something
with them, but they have to be able to have it done.
So therefore he says it's true this does not have to actually
have water hit it, but it has to be able to have
water hit it, and if there's a חציצה, chatzitzah, an obstruction, it
won't be good. So therefore you have to rinse these places with
water so that water is able to get in there even though
it doesn't need to.
ושאין ראוי לבילה,
v'she'ein rauy l'vilah, one minute, ושאין ראוי לבילה, v'she'ein rauy l'vilah, but
if it's not able to be mixed in the case of the
water, of the oil and the flour, or in this case it's
not able for water to get there because there's dirt or whatever,
then בילה מעכבת בו, bilah me'akeves bo, the mixing prevents. Now let
me say a couple of very important things about this very brief
piece. You see we're quickly doing one thing and then the next.
Here's how you wash your hair, here's how you do חפיפה, chafifah,
here's how this, here's how that. Very short little
סוגיות, sugyos, start to even call them a סוגיא sugya because there's
not even too much back and forth, that are very intense הלכות
נדה. hilchos niddah. So in terms of this issue about the חציצה,
chatzitzah, another one I'll say a few things. Number one: the fact
that he talks about rinsing underneath in the folds. What is that
saying about the assumption of do you have to wash your whole
body? Was the תקנה takanah of עזרא Ezra we mentioned before about
washing the hair include washing the body? Some say yeah, of course,
you know, look, he's talking about washing the folds, so implicitly there's
a requirement to wash the body. And his חידוש chiddush is in
addition to washing the body you also have to wash the folds
and that's what's being debated about whether you really have to wash
the fold or not because water doesn't have to get there. That's
one way of reading it. תוספות Tosafot says not necessarily. It's very
possible there's no requirement to wash the body. He's only mentioning the
folds because that's where dirt collects. Dirt collects in the folds. It
doesn't collect in the other parts of the body. And then basically
most ראשונים Rishonim assume that strictly speaking there is no requirement to
bathe the body. The only real- I mean obviously you have to
make sure there are no חציצות. chatzitzos. But whether there's a formal
rabbinic requirement to bathe the body maybe not. Maybe the only rabbinic
requirement is to wash the hair. We will see in a minute
clearly what they say is the practice was is to bathe the
body, maybe even specifically with hot water and so on. Hair we
know has to be in hot water. But there might not have
been the same strict requirement as there was with the hair. So
that's one interesting question about when did that practice come up about,
you know, doing the bathing the entire body, you know,
before going to the מקוה. mikvah. Okay, that's one issue. Now in
terms of the issue here about the obstructions and removing and ביאת
מים. vias mayim. So some ראשונים, Rishonim, first of all say, תוספות
Tosafot says and they say: Look, I don't get it. How do
you decide when you really need something and how do you decide
when it's just enough that it had the capacity to do it?
How do you know whether you really need to mix it with
water, with oil, whether you have to have the capacity to do
it?
And תוספות Tosafot says you can't even say that sometimes when something
is demanded it always needs the capacity. He gives an interesting example.
We say that every קרבן korban has to have סמיכה, smichah, but
if you don't have the capacity to do סמיכה, smichah, you're טמא,
tamei, you can send your קרבן korban in and not do סמיכה
smichah even though there isn't the capacity. So basically how do we
know when something is demanded, when capacity is enough, etc., etc. And
תוספות Tosafot doesn't really have a good answer to that question, but
he says maybe there's some דרשא. drasha. But because of that, because
it's hard to know like where did they get off saying that
this is, you know, that this middle ground. It doesn't have to
have the water of the מקוה mikvah touch it, but it's enough
that it have but needs the capacity. Some ראשונים Rishonim say that
that requirement that there be no חציצות chatzitzot in the inner parts
of your body or in the folds is only דרבנן derabbanan because
if it was really biblical, then you would actually need the מקוה
mikvah water to get there as well. That is important because a
lot of חציצה chatzitza questions that come up have to do with
parts that are inner parts of the body that are בית הסתרים.
beit hasetarim. Not so inner that they're בלוע, balua, but inner and
exposed like the mouth and so on, like braces. Or like, or
like people that have ear infections and actually have to specifically put
something in their ear to prevent water from getting there. Like at
the braces you could say if you want it on your body,
it's not you're not מקפיד makpid and we'll get to that in
a minute, it's like part of your body and it's not a
חציצה. chatzitza. But if you're putting something in your ear to prevent
water from getting there, that's exactly what a חציצה chatzitza is, something
that prevents it's performing the function of preventing water. So רב משה
Rav Moshe has a very interesting תשובה teshuva about that so does
רב עובדיה יוסף. Rav Ovadia Yosef. Part of the question is maybe
the whole issue of חציצות chatzitzot on these בית הסתרים beit hasetarim
and בית הקמטים, beit hakamtim, maybe that's just a דרבנן derabbanan concern
because of this principle of ראוי לבילה. rauy lebila. If it was
a biblical concern you'd really need water to get there. רב משה
Rav Moshe has an even more creative approach about that whole thing
even biblical it's a different type of חציצה chatzitza since water doesn't
actually have to touch the place as well. But what you do
find interesting is conceptually you can say that you need this entire
body to go be in the מקוה mikvah and the act of
טבילה tevilah is considered to take place to the entire body even
though water doesn't have to touch every part of that body. And
even though these inner folds or whatever doesn't have to you don't
always have to open your mouth and water doesn't have to get
there, but there still could be a problem of חציצה. chatzitza. So
what it also points to if you assume this is biblical is
that the חציצה chatzitza problem is not just that practically it prevents
water from getting there, because here we're saying water doesn't even have
to actually get there, that חציצה chatzitza somehow is a problem that
because there's an obstruction that somehow seen it's seen at somehow invalidating
the טבילה tevilah even though in practice it really didn't matter if
the water got there or not. So Rav Ovadia's point on ear
infections is water doesn't
really have to get there, we don't worry about חציצה? chatzitza?
No, רב עובדיה יוסף Rav Ovadia Yosef says maybe it's only דרבנן
derabbanan and he adds other concerns about אינו מקפיד eino makpid or
whatever. רב משה Rav Moshe has more interesting approach which I'm not
going to fully unpack now because we don't have the time.
So you can put something in the ear?
Well, that's debated. רב עובדיה יוסף Rav Ovadia Yosef says yes, רב
משה Rav Moshe says yes basically alright since you're pushing me I
will tell you that what רב משה Rav Moshe says is the
following. He says that he says that there's two types of חציצה.
chatzitza. There's חציצה chatzitza that's actually on the body and then there's
a חציצה chatzitza that's not really on the body but it stops
the water from getting onto the body. So he says if what
you do with the ear with the ear infection is you take
a cotton wad and you wrap it put it with like Vaseline
and you put it in the ear so the Vaseline creates a
watertight sort of you know seal. So he says like this he
says the Vaseline isn't a חציצה chatzitza because it's water soluble eventually
water can get through and that makes it not a חציצה. chatzitza.
The the the the cotton he says because it's not actually connected
to the body, it's just resting on the body, it's not really
considered a technical חציצה chatzitza in that sense. All it's really doing
is preventing water from getting onto the body, but it's not a
חציצה chatzitza because it's not on the body. And since and like
I don't know like imagine you had an invisible force field around
your ear, so then it wouldn't be a חציצה chatzitza but the
problem would be water didn't get on your on your ear. So
since you don't actually need water to get on these on the
בית הסתרים, beit hasetarim, right, it's just an issue of not having
a חציצה, chatzitza, so he manages to make this interesting conceptual distinction.
Anyway I won't go into more detail about that. Casts?
I know,
I know, I know, now ברוך השם Baruch Hashem it's much less
of an issue because they have all of these fiberglass and it's
not and they're
not the material for casts it will eventually dissolve if you soak
it enough.
Okay so that's a question about how eventually.
So Band-Aid or something that is
non- look we're going to do more חציצה chatzitza in a minute,
okay? So let's hold off some of these questions. Yes.
So is this just for women going to מקוה mikvah or this
is also like let's say for someone טמא tamei or or anything?
No, anybody.
It would be anybody. It was in the context of נדה niddah
but the requirements of going to the מקוה mikvah are absolutely no
different for a man or a woman. The only difference is possibly
is that this requirement of washing hair which was תקנת עזרא takanat
Ezra is said that it's about women presumably because women tend to
have longer hair.
And also when you say חופף את עצמו ברגל chofef et atzmo
baregel is the same idea?
That's a question about the מנהגים minhagim nowadays and how מקפיד makpid
are we with the מנהגים minhagim nowadays. But just טבילה tevilah as
a מנהג, minhag,
you don't have to necessarily go through all this to go to
the מקוה mikvah on ערב ראש השנה.
Erev Rosh Hashanah. Yeah yeah yeah. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, so that's that. That's in terms of the washing
of the body. Maybe not the whole you know again maybe not
the whole body is indicated here, maybe specifically the folds and the
idea of בית הסתרים beit hasetarim בית הקמטים beit hakamtim etcetera that
they don't you don't need water to get there but you still
can't have a חציצה chatzitza and the question whether that's דאורייתא de'oraita
or דרבנן. derabbanan. Moving on. אמר רבי בר אדא אמר רב יצחק,
Amar Rabi bar Ada Amar Rav Yitzchak, מעשה בשפחתו של
רבי, Maaseh bishifchato shel Rebbe, the story in the in the maidservant
of Rebbe. So here we had maidservant way back when I don't
think it was I don't remember if it was Rebbe, I didn't
check. Anyway remember about whether... He said do I have to go
back 24 hours or can I go back to the last time
I checked? Remember that? The whole thing about going back anyway you
can take a look. I don't remember if it was רבי. Rebbe.
שטבלה ועלתה She-tavlah v'altah she went to the מקוה mikvah and she
came out, ונמצא לה עצם חוצץ בין שיניה v'nimtza la etzem chotzetz
bein shineha she found a little, she had a little like chicken
bone between her teeth. Okay, so now the question is when did
that chicken bone get there? והצריכה רבי טבילה אחרת V'hitzricha Rebbe tvilah
acheret and רבי Rebbe said, I'm sorry you have to go do
another טבילה. tvilah. Why? This proves by the way that a חציצה
chatzitzah is a problem in the בית הסתרים. beit hasterim. Inside the
mouth is a בית הסתרים beit hasterim and here this is presumably
being brought as evidence that even though you don't need water to
get into your gums, but you cannot have חציצות chatzitzot in your
gum. Okay. ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava, it also is going to, it's
also presaging a discussion about let's say there's a doubt when the
חציצה chatzitzah got there. So here he's assuming that we have to
be concerned that it was there from before. It makes sense also,
depending if she ate recently chicken after going to the מקוה. mikvah.
I mean if she didn't eat anything after going to the מקוה
mikvah then she could be pretty certain that it was there from
before having gone to the מקוה.
mikvah. Any implication that רבי Rebbe was the one who was sleeping
with her?
What? I did not get that at all. No, but the, yes,
but no. I think the implication is that she was פרום frum
or that רבי Rebbe was concerned because it's not necessarily, no, no,
no. I think she asked him. If you go back to the
גמרא Gemara way back at the beginning talked about either asking I
think the שפחה shifcha of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel or the שפחה
shifcha of רבי Rebbe which she deals with טהרות taharot after going
to the מקוה. mikvah.
Right, right, right. It was רבן גמליאל.
Rabban Gamliel. It was רבן גמליאל.
Rabban Gamliel. Okay.
There was two stories. Was there another שפחה shifcha there later
on?
Because he doesn't want her, he doesn't want she's carrying טהרות, taharot,
she's working with תרומה, trumah, she's working with grain and stuff. She
wasn't a
כהן. kohen. It's a, okay, okay. So they were working with חולין
בטהרה. chullin b'tahara.
But she can't, but he's going to give the תרומה trumah to
a כהן. kohen.
Yeah, the גמרא Gemara before had the story with רבן גמליאל. Rabban
Gamliel. The גמרא Gemara before had the story with רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel which is the family of רבי. Rebbe. It's right, it's the
same dynasty there. And it was said, right. So anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava, now back
to the אמוראים, Amoraim, רבא Rava said, טבלה ועלתה ונמצא לה דבר
חוצץ. tavlah v'altah v'nimtza la davar chotzetz.
Now we get to the question about when you find a חציצה
chatzitzah when did it come? Before, after having gone to the מקוה.
mikvah. She went to the מקוה mikvah and then a few hours
later she saw oh my gosh, I got a חציצה chatzitzah here.
I got something on my finger. I have something in my ear.
Did I, was it there when I went to the מקוה mikvah
or not? I don't know. So what's the story?
Where were we? אם סמוך לחפיפה טבלה, Im samuch l'chafifah tavlah,
if she went to the מקוה mikvah right after having done the
חפיפה, chafifah, the, you know, the,
the washing of the hair, אינה צריכה לחזור ולטבול, eina tzricha lachzor
v'litvol, then she doesn't have to do another חפיפה chafifah and go
back into the מקוה. mikvah. ואם לאו, V'im lav, but if she
did not do her חפיפה chafifah right before, צריכה לחזור ולטבול. tzricha
lachzor v'litvol.
Then she has to do another חפיפה chafifah and go back. Why?
Because if you did the bathing right before going to the מקוה,
mikvah, then you could be pretty certain that the, that you took
care of whatever חציצות chatzitzot were there and the חציצה chatzitzah came
after having gone to the מקוה. mikvah. This is if you don't
know. If you know, then obviously it's a different story. But if
you did the bathing I don't know hours before going to the
מקוה mikvah and after that time you handled certain things, you were
outside on a sticky day, you ate certain things or whatever, then
it's quite possible that the problem arose between the חפיפה chafifah and
going to the מקוה. mikvah. And therefore you cannot assume it was
a good טבילה. tvilah. You have to go ahead and do it
again. Now again, if חפיפה chafifah means hair, then we're talking only
if in the context of when there was something in the hair.
If חפיפה chafifah means the whole body, it would apply to the
whole body. Which is why ראשונים Rishonim say that even if the
תקנת עזרא takanat Ezra was only to do bathing of the hair,
number one there is a מנהג minhag to bathe the whole body
besides the folds. And number two, not only is it a מנהג,
minhag, it's really good advice. Because if you don't bathe the whole
body and afterwards you find a חציצה, chatzitzah, you have to be
concerned that it was there from beforehand. If you've done a bathing
and then you go to the מקוה mikvah and then you find
a חציצה, chatzitzah, then you can assume it came later. Okay, one
minute. Let's finish. Okay. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, others say
not if it's סמוך samuch right nearby, but אם באותו יום שחפפה
טבלה, im b'oto yom shechafefa tavlah, אינה צריכה לחזור ולטבול. eina tzricha
lachzor v'litvol. If she found something on the same day, if she
did חפיפה chafifah on the same day,
then she doesn't have to go back to the מקוה. mikvah. ואם
לאו, V'im lav, צריכה לחזור ולטבול. tzricha lachzor v'litvol. And if it
wasn't on the same day, then she does have to assume that
it came up later, it came before she went to the מקוה
mikvah and she has to do it again. מאי בינייהו? Mai beinaihu?
What's the difference between saying if it was right before or saying
the same day? So there's an obvious difference. איכא בינייהו Icha beinaihu
לסמוך חפיפה לטבילה, lismach chafifah l'tvilah,
to do the right before the טבילה tvilah to do the חפיפה
chafifah immediately before, number one. ולימיחפף ביממא ולמיטבל בליליא. U'l'michpaf b'yimama u'l'mitbal
b'leilya.
This seems to be a נפקא מינה nafka mina on the other
side, although some ראשונים Rishonim read this as saying the same thing,
to go to do the חפיפה chafifah in the day and go
to the מקוה mikvah at night. Which means look, I can have
times when it's right before, but it's not on the same day.
If I go to, if I do my חפיפה chafifah at 5:30
and let's assume שקיעה shkiah is 6:00 or whatever, צאת tzait or
whatever, anyway and I go to the מקוה mikvah at 6:05, then
it was right before but it wasn't on the same day. 5:30
was before שקיעה, shkiah, 6:05 was after שקיעה. shkiah. So you can
have right before without being on the same day. You can
have... Doing it right before. Right before logically is what matters because
that's the reality of not having a gap, but halachically in a
formalistic way we might define it as same day unit, which I
agree does not make too much logical sense. Now this is very
important because we are going to see later today if we get
there the questions about when to do the חפיפה. Chafiffah. And as
many, you know, the practice, talking about the practice, תוספות Tosafos already,
I mentioned to you the practice of bathing your whole body, the
other practice was that you start doing the חפיפות Chafiffas maybe even
at home while it's still daytime, and then you go to the
מקוה Mikvah right before nightfall and you do another quick, you know,
running your comb through your hair, another quick check, another quick five-minute
thing, you know, right at the מקוה Mikvah itself. So then you
get both, you get doing it
beforehand, you know,
and then you also get doing it like... actually that wasn't a
good example, that's actually more relevant to what we're going to talk
later about, because there when you do it at home the day
before, it's both not as immediately beforehand and the prior day. The
benefit in that case of doing it the day before, I'm jumping
a little ahead, is that you're doing it better, you're more patient,
you have more time. Okay, so that we'll see in a minute.
But here the issue is, right, what constitutes the same period? Is
it just close, not too many minutes between them even if they're
in different days, or is it defined as the same day for
this הלכה Halacha of when can we attribute that the חציצה Chatzitzah
came later rather than earlier?
My question is you related to the... I understand about the חפיפה
Chafiffah but what about the rest of your body? You're saying נתנסלה,
Nitnaslah, נתנסלה, Nitnaslah, so the question is do you have to really
be looking for all these things or do you assume it was
a good טבילה Tvilah unless you know otherwise? Which is a very
big difference.
Well part of that is the question about whether you have to
formally do an actual washing of the whole body or not, right?
If the requirement is only to do it on the hair, then
it's saying that the rest of the body, if there was a
חציצה Chatzitzah on your body, we'll talk in a minute about what
defines a חציצה, Chatzitzah, but you'd probably be aware of it. So
you know, but
nevertheless you don't have to check beforehand. Again, the מנהג Minhag is
to do a bathing of the whole body and it's a very
strong מנהג Minhag
and
some say certainly say that at least you need to do an
inspection of the body, that you might be mandated to do or
you're not, whatever, it depends on how you read the גמרא Gemara
in בבא קמא. Bava Kama. But anyway let's assume you're mandated to
do an inspection of the body but you're not being mandated to
bathe. Nevertheless it's very good advice to do a bathing because if
you find a חציצה Chatzitzah afterwards you're going to be in trouble.
Yeah it's not from here,
the inspection, yeah that's a גמרא Gemara in בבא קמא. Bava Kama.
Back then when we were worried about טומאה Tumah and טהרה, Taharah,
most טבילה Tvilah would have been during the day because it's always...
we're getting to when you do the טבילה. Tvilah. Okay. Time up,
if we can get there. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay, so that's
טבילה. Tvilah. אמר רבא, Ammar Rava, now a lot of these are
רבא Rava as you'll notice. אשה לא תעמוד על גבי כלי חרס
ותטבול. Ishah lo ta'amod al gabei klei cheres v'tisbol. A woman should
not stand on top of pottery vessels in the מקוה Mikvah and
dunk. Maybe the floor is dirty or something, whatever, don't stand on
the upturned for example pottery vessel inside the מקוה. Mikvah. I don't
know. סבר רב כהנא למימר, Savar Rav Kahana l'meimar, רב כהנא... Rav
Kahana... well they also might have had natural מקואות Mikvahs like wells
and whatever. If you go look in the, you know, in Germany
and France or whatever from the middle age מקואות Mikvahs there were
basically natural wells and sometimes extremely deep like a woman would have
to go like 30 feet down, it was crazy anyway. Because then
the floor is not a nice
stone floor, it's a dirt floor, yeah so that...
maybe high enough
so she can stand on...
well
that too,
maybe high enough so she can stand
on...
all right also maybe high enough so that she doesn't drown. All
right so the גמרא Gemara says don't do that. סבר רב כהנא
למימר טעמא מאי? Savar Rav Kahana l'meimar ta'ama mai? רב כהנא Rav
Kahana thought why not? משום גזירת מרחצאות. Mishum gezeiras merchatzos. Because it'll
make you feel like you're in a
bathhouse. Because bathhouses aren't kosher מקואות Mikvahs and bathhouses have like stools
and things, places to sit and places to stand. So if you
have too much of an artificial sort of furniture there it'll feel
like a bathhouse and next thing you know you'll come to think
you can go to the bathhouse to go to the מקוה. Mikvah.
Right, so it feels like a whole spa. So the גמרא Gemara
says...
isn't that a kosher מקוה Mikvah to go to a bathhouse?
A bathhouse it's drawn water.
I mean if you have a bathhouse...
then it would be kosher. But yeah it could be sure okay
but in normal cases it's drawn water so it's a problem.
But nowadays I'm sorry but all the in the archaeology in Israel
they dig up a lot of these pools that they heated...
heated pools is one thing...
they were fed by...
fine but we're talking about like Roman bathhouses. Roman bathhouses aren't... a
lot of natural springs... okay even natural water if you can make
it... it depends how you get water from one place to another.
You could get it from one place to another with it being
totally fine but also if there's a human
element... Okay,
anyway, so yes, if it's natural and not שאובים she'uvim would be
fine, but there definitely were bathhouses that were not מקוואות mikvehs and
they didn't want people assuming they were. So the גמרא Gemara says,
if that's true, הא גבי סילתפא ha gabei silt'fa which is just
a plank of wood, so then you're not going to think that's
a bathhouse, it's not furniture, it's just a plank of wood, שפיר
דמי shappir dami then he assumes that that would be okay. אמר
ליה רב חמי מנהרדעא, Amar leh Rav Chama mi-Neharde'a, no, התם טעמא
מאי hasam ta'ama mai what's the reason that you don't stand on,
that you should not stand on a כלי חרס? kli cheres? It's
not because it feels like a bathhouse, but משום דבעות mishum dib'uy
because he is afraid. Because, which is funny because you think that
as we said, the whole reason she's standing on this is because
somehow it makes it, because she's afraid it makes it feel safer.
But he was somehow thinking that no, maybe if you're standing on
a vessel you're very, you know, tip over, whatever, and therefore you're
not going to do a good job. So סילתפא נמי מיבעתא silt'fa
nami bi'ita so she'll also be afraid with this with this plank
of wood. Now, I don't understand why a plank of wood makes
you afraid. Again, to us it seems like if she's doing this
she's doing it because it makes her less afraid. But he interpreted
that it was a concern about you're not going to do a
good job, you'll be too afraid, you'll be too it'll feel too
precarious and therefore those things are things you should not do. I
don't know. אמר רב שמן בר אבא,
Amar Rav
Shaman
bar Abba, אשה לא תטבול isha lo tit'bol
a woman should not go to the מקוה mikvah בנמל be-namal in
a port. Right, as it's a port, in a port. Why not?
So רש״י Rashi says, well let's read the next line in the
גמרא. Gemara. It's obvious. אף על גב דהשתא ליכא Af al gav
de-hashta leka even though now it's not there. What is it? אימור
ברדיוני נפל. Eimar bi-rad'yonei nefal. Maybe it fell off. רש״י Rashi doesn't
even know what that word means. He thinks by context it means
it fell off by sort of by movement, by scraping. Meaning that
we're afraid the way רש״י Rashi reads it is we're afraid if
you go in a port you'll get mud on your feet, that'll
be a חציצה, chatzitzah, but when you're but and even if they
all look but when I came up there was no mud. Yeah,
there was no mud because it got washed off as you were
coming up and as you were sort of rubbing your your feet
against one another, but it doesn't mean the mud wasn't on you
when you actually were in the were in the was in the
were in the river. תוספות Tosafot says that that line really is
not in the גמרא, Gemara, it's later, it was transposed here. And
תוספות Tosafot says the problem about going into a port is that
there are people around and you'll be and you'll be embarrassed and
you'll you'll rush and won't do a good job. And that might
fit into the next line of the גמרא. Gemara. So let's see
the next line of the גמרא. Gemara.
So you're saying this this bird whatever it is is is completely
just...
Well תוספות Tosafot says תוספות Tosafot says that that's not from the
original גרסא girsa of the גמרא.
Gemara. But it's nighttime, it's dark.
Yes. So meaning why how are you anyway going at night into
this type of a place? Yeah, I mean that's also a
we'll see in a minute whether you're going at night or day
but presumably yes you are going at night. Yeah, so I mean
but again that would be a reason why not to do it.
Okay, right, okay. אבוה דשמואל, Avu'a de-Shmuel, the father of שמואל, Shmuel,
עביד לבנתיה avid le-banatei made for his daughters מקוואות ביומי ניסן mikva'os
be-yomei Nisan מקוואות mikvehs in ניסן Nisan in the springtime, and ומפצי
u-maftzei
and mats like ביומי תשרי be-yomei Tishrei in תשרי. Tishrei. Now let's
start with this. Why is he making mats in תשרי? Tishrei? Because
in תשרי Tishrei they're going in the river and or in whatever
natural bodies well river let's say. And therefore they need mats. Why
do they need mats if they're going in the river? Well number
one is is because for רש״י Rashi so they don't get muddy.
For תוספות Tosafot they need for privacy. Are the mats are the
mats on the floor for their feet or are they screens? So
that's the debate of רש״י תוספות. Rashi Tosafot. By the way assuming
רש״י Rashi is on the floor you see that there are some
things that are not this משום דבעות mishum dib'uy afraid. You have
to assume that the problem before about the plank or whatever was
still something that was basically maybe on some type of a you
know some type of a plank on some part on a platform
so that you could be but if it's just a simple mat
then obviously you're not afraid and that would be okay. So that's
that's the issue about תשרי. Tishrei. Now why did they have to
do different in ניסן? Nisan? Because ניסן Nisan is the spring, it's
been after the whole fall period, after the rainy period. And what
you're concerned about in the spring in there is that in the
in the river there could be a lot of rainwater, there could
be also a lot of melted snow water. Why does that matter?
Because rivers this is the way רש״י Rashi explains it, rivers are
running water. Running water normally as you know a מקוה mikvah has
to be stationary water, it can't be running water. Running water is
okay if the body of water is a natural running water body
natural running water. It's not rainwater, it's a river, it's natural naturally
running water. But there's a problem. If the even if it's a
river and the water is naturally running, if the majority of the
water in the river at this time is not from under underwater
wells springs but it's from rainwater or melted snow then it can't
it doesn't have a status of a river right now. It doesn't
have a status of a naturally running water because most of the
water is not from the is not running water. And therefore you
cannot use a a river when there's a concern that the majority
of the water is rain and melted snow which actually has practical
implication now because everybody assumes oh it's okay I'm going to be
on vacation I'm on whatever but you know I can go in
the pond I can go in the river. First of all a
lot
of
To figure out whether it's a majority. So that's why he could
not have them using the rivers during ניסן Nissan and he had
to make for them מקוואות. Mikvaos. Now, that's the general פשט pshat
that's accepted there. However, I should point out a very important רש"י
Rashi because he has a commentary that he's rejecting. And the commentary
he's rejecting is that actually the problem of the
rainwater was not the fact that it was running and because it
was mostly rain it had a station. The problem was was that
it now was not a—it was not mostly מים חיים. mayim chayim.
It was not mostly live water. Because in the תורה Torah and
here's a very fascinating point. When the תורה Torah says that a
זב zav has to go to the מקווה, mikva, it says that
he has to go to מים חיים, mayim chayim, live water, which
means basically either a river or a wellspring. It doesn't tell you
what a זבה zavah has to do to go to be טהורה.
tehorah. So it's not unreasonable to assume that a זבה zavah would
require מים חיים. mayim chayim. If—and there are some גאונים Geonim that
actually said a זבה zavah requires מים חיים. mayim chayim. Here's a
little bit of a למדות, lomdus, which is that if a זבה
zavah has to requires מים חיים mayim chayim and nowadays all women
are treated as זבות, zavos, then you cannot have a man-made מקווה.
mikva. You can only have a natural wellspring as a מקווה. mikva.
So all the ראשונים Rishonim reject that interpretation. They say absolutely not,
a זבה zavah does not need מים חיים, mayim chayim, but some
גאונים Geonim say they do. And they say that's what's going on
here with שמואל. Shmuel. Because there was a lot of rainwater, then
it was no longer מים חיים mayim chayim and you couldn't use
the river. So the obvious question is then, okay, so how does
it help by building them מקוואות? mikvaos? Right, that's the problem. Ah,
because we think of מקוואות mikvaos as man-made and collected rainwater. But
you could also do something which creates מים חיים. mayim chayim. When
I think of מים חיים mayim chayim I normally think of like
a geyser, but all מים חיים mayim chayim means is natural water
from under the ground. So all the
wells are מים חיים. mayim chayim. So it could be that he
dug for them wells. So there's a Geonic read of this סוגיה,
sugya, which is he had to do it to ensure they had
מים חיים. mayim chayim. Thankfully all of the ראשונים Rishonim reject that.
Now, you could even say how could anybody have that הוה אמינא,
havah amina, where are women, you know, during their time going to—they're
going to מקוואות. mikvaos. How could you think that we require מים
חיים. mayim chayim. But as I told you before, in the period
of the ראשונים, Rishonim, most מקוואות mikvaos were wells. And therefore if
most women are anyway using a well as a מקווה, mikva, you
could say, well, you have to go to מים חיים. mayim chayim.
Thankfully that interpretation was completely rejected, was completely rejected and that's why
we can have man-made מקוואות. mikvaos. But that was one read of
this. Yes, because it says, whatever, obviously by practice—so
where do we get the idea that you can טובל toivel in
the ocean?
Oh, well that also I mean the משניות מקוואות Mishnayos Mikvaos makes
that clear. Okay, you know, that you can טובל toivel in the
ocean—which has got more rainwater than ocean water? Yeah, yeah, no, no,
right, right. Okay so now, anyway, so the
river—the problem was—רש"י Rashi says the
problem was that the water was running. But some of the גאונים
Geonim say no, everybody agrees the problem was that there was too
much rainwater. So רש"י Rashi says too much rainwater, you can't have
running water. The גאונים Geonim say too much rainwater, it's no longer
מים חיים mayim chayim and you have to
have—so rainwater—running water is only okay if it's pure river water and
not—not pure, majority river water.
Okay, okay, right, majority of rainwater.
Okay, we have
this—I remember this from the גמרא. gemara.
Okay so now the גמרא gemara goes on. Okay so that is
obviously very important in terms of actually a position that's rejected. Now
and also being aware that not all natural bodies can necessarily immediately
be assumed to be good מקוואות. mikvaos. Now the גמרא gemara goes
on. אמר רב, Amar Rav, now אמר רב גידל אמר רב: Amar
Rav Gidel Amar Rav: נתנה
תבשיל לבנה. Natna tavshil livnah. If a woman gave some, you know,
some type of a cooked dish to her son. וטבלה
ועלתה, V'tavlah v'altah,
and then she went to the מקווה mikva right after. ועלתה לא
עלתה לה טבילה. V'altah lo alsah lah tvilah. It's not a good
טבילה. tvilah. אף על
גב דהשתא ליכא, Af al gav d'hashta leka, even though now, what
do you mean? She says look, I don't have any of that
food left on my body. You know, okay I was handling the
dirt, you know, whatever sticky food, but it's not on me now,
so it's not a חציצה. chatzitzah. No, אימר בארדגוני נפל, eimar b'ardaguni
nafal, maybe it fell off when you were, you know, when you're
rubbing and you're going into the מקווה. mikva. So basically here again
is the importance of doing the washing and the checking right before
going to the מקווה mikva because even if you do relatively innocent
things, if it's handling sticky items, you have to be concerned that
you might still have it on you even if you inspect afterwards
and don't find—so could be—it could be an
issue. We're skipping an עמוד amud in the גמרא. gemara. אמר אמי
בר אבא. Amar Ami bar Abba. הני רבדי דכוסליתא. Hani rabdi d'kuslisa.
The certain scab over a wound. עד תלתא יומי לא הוי. Ad
tlata yomei lo hayvei. Until three days it's not considered a חציצה
chatzitzah because it's soft and it's maybe considered like part of the
skin. מכאן ואילך הוי. Mikan v'eilach hayvei. After it gets hard then
it's—it's considered maybe not part of the skin and—or maybe it goes
outside of the boundaries of the wound and it is a חציצה.
chatzitzah.
You'd have to actually remove the scab.
Alright, I'll talk in a minute. אמר מר עוקבא: Amar Mar Ukva:
לכלוך שבעין, Lifluf sheba'ayin, the sort of the, you know, not the
dirt— mucus in the eyes, לח lach if it's moist אינו חוצץ,
eino chotzetz, it's not a חציצה, chatzitza, then it's like a type
of a liquid and it's sort of permeable. יבש חוצץ yavesh chotzetz
if it's dry. אימתי נקרא יבש? Eimatai nikra yavesh? When is it
called dry? משעה שמתחיל לירק Mishe'sha she'matchil le'yarek from the time it
starts to turn a greenish type of a color. Lovely. אמר
שמואל, Amar Shmuel, כחול שבתוך העין, kachol she'betoch ha'ayin, כחול kachol was
a type of things they applied makeup but also some type of
thing they applied in the eye as a type of a salve
or something. So if it's inside the eye, אינו חוצץ, eino chotzetz,
it's not a חציצה chatzitza because it's moist there and again presumably
water permeable. ושעל גבי העין V'she'al gabi ha'ayin on the outside of
the eye, חוצץ. chotzetz. That it is, because then it's not kept
moist and it hardens and it's a חציצה. chatzitza. אם היו עיניה
פורחות Im hayu eineha porchot and if her eyes were like fluttering
her eyelids, אפילו על גבי העין אינו חוצץ afilu al gabi ha'ayin
eino chotzetz then not, because then it remains loose and the water
can get through.
What am I saying?
What was that last part? If her eyes if she's constantly fluttering
her eyelids, then whatever they put on remains sort of more powdery
and loose. Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, פתחה עיניה ביותר
או עמצה עיניה ביותר, patcha eineha b'yoter o imtza eineha b'yoter, if
she opens up her eyes too much or closes them too tight,
לא עלתה לה טבילה, lo alta la tevila, not good. Why? Because
that causes the folds of her body to be different than they
more naturally are. Things right would be so it causes skin that's
normally exposed to be folded over and then water won't get through.
We learned before water doesn't have to get into the area that
is normally folded over, but if areas are unnaturally folded over, it's
a problem if water didn't get there.
You shouldn't open your eyes open then?
Well not too much, no, not like excessively. Anyway, I'm going to
say something and then end about the conclusion about
this. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, האשה לא תטבול אלא כדרך
גדילתה. ha'isha lo titbol ela k'derech gdilata. A woman should only go
into the מקוה mikvah in a natural way. What does this mean?
So this is again addressing the issue of before that the folds
of the exposed skin in the folds of her body should be
natural. If she's holding her body in an unusual way, then okay
she might say well this way I'll get more of that fold
of those fold areas exposed, but it'll get other area folded over.
So you should be a very natural posture in the
מקוה. mikvah. כדתנן Ki'd'tnan like we taught, and this is interesting because
we discuss a lot when we do סממנים sammanim about drawing on
the world of נגעים negaim of צרעת. tzara'at. So here also is
drawing from the world of צרעת tzara'at that the פסוק pasuk says
that the כהן kohen looks for the mark לכל מראה עיני הכהן
lechol mareh einei hakohen to the entire vision of the eyes of
the כהן, kohen, which means that if there's a mark on the
body, a צרעת tzara'at spot on the body, then a place which
is not normally exposed, then you don't have to worry about it.
So how do you determine normally exposed? Just like the issue before,
the places of normal folds as opposed to the places of normally
exposed. So you figure out how does a person normally stand. So
here's how you figure
it
out: האיש נראה כעודר וכמוסק זיתים. ha'ish ne'ereh k'oder u'mosek zeitim. So
a man would be like hoeing or like picking up olives. So
if you hoe or you pick up olives, you know, you sort
of extend your body to a certain degree, but not excessively. So
in those you're seen you sort of look at natural configurations of
your body when you're stretching to a natural degree and those are
the areas that are considered exposed, other areas not.
נגע Nega in the in the underarm then would be a problem
right? Because when you're picking olives you have to raise your hand.
Yeah, but it depends how far you have to raise and how
much, so those that's the question. האשה, Ha'isha, a woman, נראית כעורגת
nire'et k'oreget like she would be if she was knitting, או כמניקה
את בנה o k'menika et b'nah or nursing her child. רש״י Rashi
says that the reason for two examples is one is to speak
about how much of her underarms are exposed, like when you're knitting
your arms are a little bit obviously removed from your body, and
the other is like how much of the sort of of the
pubic area or the side area when you're sitting down and, you
know, and nursing, it's sort of a squatting and so on. So
the point is you're supposed to be natural and you would say
okay but maybe if I expose more it's better, but the גמרא's
Gemara point is no, if you're unnatural like with the eyes, you
know, you would cause other areas to be covered up. So you
have to be very natural. Now we just read that whole list,
some of those things like were pretty reasonable requirements, you know okay
fine whatever, so stand in a natural way when you go to
the מקוה. mikvah. Others seem a little bit unreasonable, like you can't
have scabs, what does that mean that you have to rip off
scabs and so on? And there are some horrific stories about,
you know,
going back to the old issue about a young bride or young
wives, about rabbis that would rip off scabs of their young wives
who refused to, you know, do it. Of a baby?
Of their yeah, very young.
I don't know exactly baby, but very young. Anyway,
anyway, so there's a line that ended this גמרא Gemara that there
are stories. I can show you. It's in the שולחן ערוך Shulchan
Aruch quoted by some of the commentators of the שולחן ערוך Shulchan
Aruch around this
הלכה. halacha. Okay, anyway, there's a line in this גמרא Gemara that
most ראשונים Rishonim have that said, ולית הלכתא ככל הני שמעתתא. v'leit
hilchata k'chol hanei shma'at'ta. דאיתמר לתרץ איתמר. d'is'mar l'tareis etmar. That we
don't have that. I know, but if you look תוספות Tosafos has
that line and whatever, that the הלכה halacha is not like anything
we just said. All of these requirements are only for טהרות, taharos,
not, you know, when we have extra stringencies for the water of
the פרה, parah, not for going to the מקוה mikvah for women
and for נדה niddah and so on. So he says, פסקי ריאביה,
Piskei Ri-aviyot, he says, here it is, אחר זה כתב ספר רבינו
חננאל,
achar ze kasav
sefer
Rabbeinu Chananel, מצות ספרים, mitzvos svarim, ולית הלכתא ככל הני שמעתתא דאיתמר
הני לטהרה ולא לבעל קרי, v'lais hilchasa k'chol hani sh'maitata d'etmar hani
l'tahara v'lo l'ba'al keri, אמר ריש לקיש לא תיפול ולא תיסתר, amar
Reish Lakish lo tipol v'lo seiser, etc., etc.
Anyway, he has a whole discussion, but clearly almost all of the
things we said here are much more stringent than the requirements are
clearly more מחמיר machmir than the requirements that appear in מסכת מקואות
Masechet Mikvaos that talk about what are the concerns of חציצה. chatzitza.
So there's a very important question about how much we פוסקין paskin
any of what we just said on the almost the entire עמוד
א'. amud aleph. Okay, I'm not going to discuss it now. אמר
ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, moving on. I just
did that. אמר רבה בר בר חנה נימא אחת קשורה חוצצת. Amar
Rabbah bar bar Chana nima achas k'shura chotzetza. If one hair is
knotted on itself, it's a חציצה. chatzitza. Now, normally we say the
body can't be a חציצה, chatzitza, but that means things like scabs
couldn't be a חציצה, chatzitza, you know, things that are natural or
let's say there's a discussion about women cutting their nails. So some
of the פוסקים poskim want to say, so normally those that say
you have to cut your nails is a concern about dirt underneath
it, and there's a lot of discussion nowadays because, you know, it's
always been very difficult, you know, some women are super מחמיר machmir
about this, others it's a very big issue cutting their nails, and
you know, פוסקים poskim basically say, yeah, it's all really about dirt,
so if it's a real big issue for you, you know, just
clean them very well and so on. But some wanted to make
it even a bigger deal and say that, no, if your nails
have gotten to a point where they need to be cut or
let's say your hair's gotten to a point where it needs to
be cut, so then the part that you're going to cut off
is extraneous and it's a חציצה chatzitza on the part that will
eventually be exposed when you cut the nail. Now, that of course
seems complete absurd and the basic point is a body cannot be
a חציצה chatzitza on itself. This is all part of your body
right now, it's not a חציצה. chatzitza.
But that is true, but when you actually have a hair knotted,
okay, water is not getting into the knot, okay? So even if
you don't call it technically a חציצה, chatzitza, and here it is
really that it's sort of whatever, there's a problem that water's not
getting into the knot and that's an issue. So he says if
it's אחת, achas, one hair knotted on itself, that's a problem, water
can't get into the knot. שלש, Shalosh, three hairs, אינו חוצצת, eino
chotzetza, you're not it's not going to be a very tight knot
if three hairs are whatever. Well, yeah, it's a question, is that
a braid? Maybe technically, but of course we don't do it. שתים,
Shtayim, איני יודע, eini yodeia, two I don't know if that's a
tight enough knot or not. רבי יוחנן אמר אין לנו
אלא אחת. Rabbi Yochanan amar ein lanu ela achas. No, only one
hair is a problem, more than that is not a problem. אמר
רב יצחק, Amar Rav Yitzchak, now the problem is here, now we
get to finally after all those technical issues.
How should you know if one hair is knotted?
Well, that's why you go back to the earlier thing, you're supposed
to do the washing and the combing and all of that and
the assumption being that the combing will get out at least, unless
you're lice-prone and
you have to check every single No, but the point
is that you're supposed
to run your hands through your hair, you do the best you
can.
No, no, that's not what it says here. No, it's it doesn't
say you're doing the best you can.
I know, but
it it gives you an impossible standard to follow.
Well, let's, can we read the next line and see if it's
impossible because the next line is going to make it much more
reasonable, okay? Four hairs? אמר רב יצחק, Amar Rav Yitzchak, no, no,
no, let's read the next line. אמר רב יצחק דבר תורה רובו
המקפיד עליו חוצץ. Amar Rav Yitzchak devar Torah rubo hamakpid alav chotzez.
Biblically, if you the only thing that's a חציצה chatzitza biblically is
if it's the majority of the body and you're מקפיד, makpid, you
don't want it on.
Majority it's on the majority of the body?
Yes, it covers the majority of the body. So it's basically almost
impossible to have a biblical חציצה. chatzitza. What could it be, a
body cast? You know, I mean what could it be, I guess
if you got into, you fell into a whole slime pit or
something. Okay, it has to be on the majority of the body
and you don't want it on.
Like this mud we were talking about before on their feet.
Right, it's all rabbinic. It's all rabbinic. רובו ואינו מקפיד עליו, Rubo
ve'eino makpid alav, if it's the majority and you don't really mind
it, maybe that would be the body cast, you want it on
you so for a particular reason, what? A mud bath. Okay, then
אינו חוצץ, eino chotzez, it's not a problem. Where was I? רובו
ואינו מקפיד עליו אינו חוצץ. Rubo ve'eino makpid alav eino chotzez. And
similarly if it's a minority, even if you are מקפיד, makpid, it's
also not a חציצה. chatzitza. You need both majority and מקפיד. makpid.
וגזרו, Vegozru, the Rabbis made an edict, על רובו שאינו מקפיד משום
רובו המקפיד. al rubo she'eino makpid mishum rubo hamakpid. If it's on
a majority even if you're not מקפיד, makpid, it's still a problem
because that's only one step away from the problematic case, the majority
and not wanting it. וגזרו על מיעוטו המקפיד משום רובו המקפיד. Vegozru
al mi'uto hamakpid mishum rubo hamakpid. And also if it's this is
the much more bigger case, a minority that you're מקפיד makpid on,
also no good because it at least has the מקפיד makpid aspect,
you don't want it on, and that's one step away from the
biblical case. So the one case though that isn't a problem, that's
not a חציצה chatzitza is a minority that you don't care about.
And now the גמרא Gemara says, oh, why do we let you
get away with that? So the גמרא Gemara says, ונגזור נמי על
מיעוטו שאינו מקפיד משום מיעוטו המקפיד. v'nigzor nami al mi'uto she'eino makpid
mishum mi'uto hamakpid.
Let's also say you can't have a minority that you don't care
about because it'll lead to a case of a minority that you
do. care about. So the גמרא Gemara says, no. היא גופא גזירה.
hi gufa gezeira. The whole problem about a minority, a minority that
you do care about, is itself a safeguard. ואנן ניקום ונגזור גזירה
לגזירה? ve'anan nekum venigzor gezeira legezeira? You want us to make a
safeguard on a safeguard? So of course they do it all the
time, but thankfully sometimes they don't do it and he says, no
we don't. Now this is probably one of the most important principles
for הלכות נדה, hilchos nida, which is the following: The מנהג minhag
is, of course, that women take off anything, even מיעוט המקפיד miut
hamakpid and so on. They try to remove any חציצה. chatzitza. But
if there's ever an issue, then we go to the basic הלכה
halacha which is, if it's a minority that you're not מקפיד, makpid,
it's not a problem. And the big questions come on how do
you define מקפיד. makpid. And I'm not going to get into a
discussion right now, but I will just give you a simple point
which is, the big issue is around things that you want on
your body now, but in the big picture, well I'll talk about
I'll say something about now versus I can't get into it because
we have to go further, but I'll say one or two things
about that. But the big issue is: something you really want on
your body all the time is clearly
a non-מקפיד. makpid. But there are things that you want on your
body now but you would ideally not want, like a cast, braces.
Right? I wish these damn excuse me darn braces were off. Okay?
But and they and they really are like annoying the heck out
of me, but at some level I want them on because they're
all, you know, ideally I really don't, my parents are forcing me,
but assuming it's not your parents, okay? At some level I want
them on. Right. Right. Anyway, okay, getting back to our state. So
that's an interesting question about is that considered מקפיד makpid or not.
Now a case that would seem easier would be a case when
it's not really annoying you and it's just something like an ideal
thing. Like so I've got a I've got a cast.
Ideally would I want my cast off? Yeah, but right now if
you ask me, I totally want it on. It's not like the
braces where I'm upset every minute that it's on. I totally want
it on right now. So הרב עובדיה יוסף Harav Ovadia Yosef pretty
much considers almost all things that are medically necessary as אינו מקפיד.
eino makpid. You know, with maybe some discussion around things that are
super annoying you like the braces. But a lot of other פוסקים,
poskim, including רב משה, Rav Moshe, are more ambivalent about it because
they say since at some ideal level you wouldn't want it there,
maybe that constitutes מקפיד. makpid. And that creates a lot of issues
as you can imagine. Okay, you know, every when I'm giving you
basic principles here. Now Rachel's issue about nail polish is interesting. You
know, some פוסקים poskim say you have to remove nail polish, you
know, but some say no. Only if it's chipped do you have
to remove it because then it's because then it's מקפיד. makpid. But
if you're because you don't really want it this way. But you
know, but if you reapply a new coat, then it's not מקפיד
makpid and then you definitely want it on. So anyway, so that's
an interesting issue around that.
Probably in this country or...
Who would ever let you get away with that? Right, right.
Actually,
I know one
in
nail polish.
Okay, now.
And then after the rabbi intervened.
Okay. Okay,
now I want to say one more thing and then I do
want to move on. And the one more thing I want to
say is going back to the hair issue. Because while I said
most of the issues are around around
מקפיד, makpid, some issues are around רוב. rov. Why? When do you
ever get רוב? rov? Because some ראשונים rishonim say because of all
this emphasis on hair and knotted hair and whatever, right? Why didn't
you say one knotted hair is a מיעוט שאינו מקפיד? miut she'eino
makpid? Right? So some say that hair actually is determined differently when
it comes to issues of רוב. rov. And it's either the majority
of the body or the majority of the hair. And if it's
on the majority of the hair, even if it's not מקפיד, makpid,
it's still a problem. Now you still say when do you have
things majority of the hair? But you know what? Sometimes you do.
What? Braids or hair dye or all types of things. Now hair
dye they mostly say is not a problem because they say it
gets absorbed into the hair itself and is not on the surface
of the hair. Okay? But anyway, that's where you get some of
those issues. And the knotted some will say that the problem with
the knotted is really only a problem when it's the majority of
the hairs that are knotted. If it's an individual hair that's knotted,
then what... I understand. So that's why the process of תורה שבעל
פה Torah she'baal peh is an ongoing process of learning and interpreting.
Okay. Is these a problem?
Why? I missed it.
Because it might be. But but hair might be considered by itself
and even if you have even רוב שאינו מקפיד rov she'eino makpid
could be an issue.
You establish standard that is impossible.
I understand. But this next statement about רוב rov and מקפיד makpid
puts things in manageable proportions. Right.
But then רוב שאינו מקפיד rov she'eino makpid. אינו חוצץ. chotzetz. So
it wouldn't be a problem.
Except that hair, if the majority of the hair is braided, then
it's רוב שאינו מקפיד. דרבנן derabanan it's חוצץ.
What about like a ring? If you always wear that.
Right. So then it's probably אינו מקפיד. eino makpid. But it depends.
Yeah, it depends if you take it off from time to time
that cases... What is המקפיד? hamakpid? המקפיד hamakpid is the opposite. המקפיד
hamakpid is you you're annoyed that it is on you. You want
it off. Okay. So, alright, that is that. Like I said, every
every thing here is an entire סימן siman in שולחן ערוך. Shulchan
Aruch. Okay, every few lines here is major הלכות נדה. hilchos nida.
Let's move on though now to the I want at least do
for for try to get through this about when a woman goes
to the מקוה. mikveh. Okay, this is the next very important גמרא.
Gemara. אמר רב נידה בזמנה אינה טובלת אלא בלילה. Amar Rav nida
bizmana eina toveles ela balaylah. A נידה nida going back to the
to the הלכה halacha before the חומרת רבי זירא, chumras Rabi Zeira,
who went waited seven days of טומאה tumah as I mentioned and
then she went and didn't have to be clean days, so she
she had to go at night. She can't go during day seven.
She's טמאה tamei during day seven. So she has to go at
night. שלא בזמנה, She-lo bi'zmanah, if she's going after day, after the
night of seven, she's going late, day eight, day nine or whatever,
טובלת בין ביום בין בלילה. tovelet bein bi-yom bein bi-layla. She can
go in the morning. So if she missed the night of seven,
go in the morning of eight. רבי יוחנן אמר בין בזמנה בין
שלא בזמנה, Rabbi Yochanan amar bein bi-zmanah bein she-lo bi-zmanah,
whether at the time or not the time, אינה טובלת אלא בלילה.
einah tovelet ela ba-layla. She can only go at night. So even
if she missed night seven, she has to go night eight, not
day eight. Why? Why?
משום סרך בתה, mishum serach bitah, because of the cleaving of her
daughter, which means as opposed to now when women learn הלכות נדה
hilchos niddah through a כלה kallah teacher, which has a lot of
issues to it, in the past they used to be more observant
of their the daughters of their mothers' practice and maybe more open
about discussing it and so on. So this girl will remember, I
remember my mom used to go to the מקוה mikvah during the
daytime. So therefore, she's going to go to the מקוה mikvah during
the daytime, but she's going to wind up going day seven. And
if it's not the way we practice נדה niddah now, but the
way נדה niddah was originally, then day seven the טבילה tevilah is
completely not good, because the woman can't is not is טמאה tamei
through day seven and can only go to the מקוה mikvah at
the night. As the woman's טובלת? tovelet? Okay, so you know that
gets to the type of לא פלוג lo palug that we don't
make those distinctions and we make general rules. We don't make case
by case.
But it's dangerous in some neighborhoods.
I know, we're getting there, we're getting there. Okay, so that's the
first rule is don't go on the day of the eighth because
it'll lead to going day of seven and then it won't be
a good mik... good. אף רב הדר ביה, Af Rav hadar beih,
and even Rav who said you can go on the day of
the eighth, he reversed himself. דאמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר רב,
De-amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi amar Rav, נדה בין בזמנה בין שלא
בזמנה, niddah bein bi-zmanah bein she-lo bi-zmanah, we have another teaching in
the name of Rav that whether on the day seven whether on
the time or not even if it's day eight, אינה טובלת אלא
בלילה einah tovelet ela ba-layla משום סרך בתה, mishum serach bitah, it
has to be at night because of the daughter. Now the גמרא
Gemara says, עסקינן askin רב אידי בנרש, Rav Idi be-Narash, so רב
אידי Rav Idi made a תקנה takkanah however in נרש, Narash, which
was his town, למיטבל ביומא דתמניא, le-mitval bi-yoma de-tamanya, you can go
on day eight. Obviously not day seven again because that is still
biblically not good, but on day eight, משום אריוותא mishum aryavata because
of lions. Okay, apparently were around at night, or maybe it means
cougars or whatever. Anyway, רב אחא בר יעקב בפפוניא, Rav Acha bar
Yaakov be-Papunya, רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov
made a תקנה takkanah in his place פפוניא Papunya משום גנבי mishum
ganvi that there were robbers out, there were bad people out at
night, so you only go go during the day, the day eight.
רב יהודה בפומבדיתא Rav Yehuda be-Pumbedita משום צינה, mishum tsina, רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda said it was too cold so at night so he
said go in the day. רבא במחוזא Rava be-Mechuza and רבא Rava
in his town was מחוזא Mechuza משום אבולי mishum avulei
which is a question what it means, some say it means that
there were like the guards of the city wouldn't let them back
in or other types of concerns. So what you see here is
that although you're not supposed rabbinically go during day eight, they allowed
it when there were extenuating circumstances. Now I know I'm just going
to go three more minutes because I want to just finish the
discussion of when she goes, if people have to leave fine, but
three more minutes to finish this up. אמר ליה Amar lei רב
פפא Rav Pappa לרבא le-Rava or לאביי, le-Abaye, or אביי לרבא. Abaye
le-Rava. רב פפא Rav Pappa said to אביי Abaye and רבא. Rava.
Now again, remember רב פפא Rav Pappa was the one who yesterday
was pushing חומרא דרבי זירא chumra de-Rabbi Zeira and trying to universalize
it. And here and רבא Rava was giving him a little pushback.
Here you see it him again playing this role. And look at
the phrase he uses. It's no longer בנות ישראל. benot Yisrael. Look
at how he introduces it. מכדי, Michdi, let's let's take a look.
השתא, Hashta, nowadays, כולהו ספק זבות שוינהו רבנן. kulu safek zavot shavinuhu
rabbanan.
The rabbis have considered all women to be possible זבות. zavot. So
he took חומרא דרבי זירא, chumra de-Rabbi Zeira, he said כולהו, kulu-hu,
he universalized it, right, all women are now rabbinically treated as ספק
זבות. safek zavot. So רב פפא Rav Pappa actually was key to
this thing, turning רבי זירא'ס Rabbi Zeira's חומרא chumra of בנות ישראל
benot Yisrael into being universalized and treated as a rabbinic requirement. So
now that all women are rabbinically treated as זבות, zavot, so a
זבה, zavah, a נדה niddah can't go during day seven, but a
זבה zavah can go on the day seven of the clean days
because then she's allowed to, מקצת היום ככולו. miktzat hayom ke-kulo. ליטבלו
ביומא דשביעתא. Litvelu bi-yoma de-shivata. Go on on day seven of the
clean days, since a woman is waiting seven clean days anyway. So
he says no, משום דרבי שמעון, mishum de-Rabbi Shimon, because of רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, דתניא de-tanya we taught in a ברייתא baraita אחר
תטהר, achar tithar, afterwards she should become טהורה. tehorah. אחר אחר לכולן.
Achar achar le-kulan. You have to have one sort of period of
טהרה taharah שלא תהא טומאה מפסקת ביניהן, she-lo tehai tumah mafseket beineihan,
if the bleeding it uproots all seven clean days. And then we
get to the key line, רבי שמעון אומר אחר תטהר אחר מעשה
תטהר, Rabbi Shimon omer achar tithar achar ma'aseh tithar, after she goes
to the מקוה, mikvah, which means she could even go to the
מקוה mikvah on day seven of the clean days. אבל אמרו חכמים
אסור לעשות כן, Aval amru chachamim asur la'asot ken, but the rabbis
said you shouldn't go to the מקוה mikvah on day seven. Why?
שמא תבא לידי ספק, Shema tavo lidei safek, because you'll go to
the מקוה mikvah on day seven, you'll have sex and you'll bleed
later on day seven and it'll retroactively uproot everything and you'll wind
up of having sex when you were a זבה. zavah. So therefore,
don't go on day seven, it'll lead to having sex on day
seven and it'll lead to all these problems. So what this comes
up is that now women now go to the מקוה mikvah at
the night of seven, not because of, at least the way it's
framed, because they're of a נדה niddah category which goes at night,
but because they're a זבה, zavah, but even as a זבה zavah
in seven clean days which technically can go on day seven, you're
not supposed to because it might lead to having sex
and then
the then day
the menstrual period makes them a נידה niddah but they're given the
law of a זבה zavah of seven clean days. And because of
this hybrid nature, they're going to the מקווה mikvah as נידות niddot
go to the מקווה. mikvah. They go to the מקווה mikvah at
night, although it's night of seven clean days, not night of the
seven days from the onset. And that's conceptually to me that's more
what it's about. The way the גמרא Gemara here frames it, it's
about this concern about she'll have sex and she'll bleed and it'll
retroactively be a problem. The one thing I want to leave you
with, which is the big practical question, is in this גמרא, Gemara,
you could only when they were discussing earlier going to the מקווה
mikvah because of extenuating circumstances in the day, they only suggested day
eight, they couldn't suggest day seven because they were talking about biblical
נידה niddah and day seven the מקווה mikvah wouldn't have counted. There's
a very important question nowadays where we technically day seven can work
because it's day seven of the clean days. In extenuating circumstances, can
you go to the מקווה mikvah on day seven, not day eight?
And that's one very important question. And then רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam
also has a twist, which is since the concern of day seven
is that she might have sex with her husband and so on,
what if she went on day seven in a way that she
was never home and in private with her husband until the nightfall?
Maybe that would be okay as well, and that leads to very
important הלכתי halakhic questions about when we allow when it's okay for
women to go to the מקווה mikvah not only on day eight
in extenuating circumstances but even on day seven.